<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Love and obedience or, Christs precept and promise. Being a sermon preached on Whitsunday last, 28 of May, 1637. in Guild-hall chappell, before the right honorable the Lord Major of this city of London.</title>
            <author>Freake, William</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633242</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633242</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174045</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00055)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174045)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2115:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Love and obedience or, Christs precept and promise. Being a sermon preached on Whitsunday last, 28 of May, 1637. in Guild-hall chappell, before the right honorable the Lord Major of this city of London.</title>
                  <author>Freake, William</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Okes dwelling in little-Saint Bartholomewes.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpiece, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A², B-C⁴, D¹.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XIV, 15-16 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174045:1"/>
            <p>Love and Obedience OR, Chriſts Precept and Promiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being a Sermon Preached on Whitſunday</hi> laſt, 28. of May, 1637. in Guild-hall chappell, before the right Honorable the Lord Major of this City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Freake</hi> Miniſter of the Word of God.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Samuel, 15.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Behold, to Obey is better then ſacrifice, and to hearken <hi>is better</hi> then the fat of Rams.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>Iohn Okes</hi> dwelling in little-Saint Bartholmewes. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:174045:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174045:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Sir Edward Bromfield</hi> Knight, Lord Major of this honorable City; and to the reſt of the right Worſhipful Court of Aldermen, with the right Worſhipful <hi>William Abell,</hi> and <hi>Iames Garrard,</hi> Eſquires, Shriefes of this Honourable Citty for this yeare.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>William Freake</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word, wiſheth in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of this his ſervice, all reall happineſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to this life and a better.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right honorable and right Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſhew reaſons for my Dedication of this Sermon, and my ſervice therein to <hi>your Honour,</hi> and to this <hi>City,</hi> may bee expected by ſome that have not knowne me and my courſe; but they are well known almoſt to all that know me, to be ſuch, and of that <hi>Nature,</hi> that if I ſhould neglect this duty, the World might well crie ſhame upon me. <hi>I</hi> have beene above <hi>thirty foure yeares</hi> imploied here wholy, and within the Verge of this City: I haue received the greateſt good that I enjoy in my preſent courſe from the reverend Miniſtry of this City. <hi>I</hi> have had my firſt incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb facs="tcp:174045:3"/>in this <hi>way,</hi> from a <hi>worſhipfull Society</hi> of this City. What <hi>I</hi> hope to enjoy during life, hath beene the free gift of this <hi>honourable Court of Aldermen,</hi> and of this <hi>Citty.</hi> All which are iuſt incentives to a reſpective thankefulneſſe from me.</p>
            <p>But <hi>I</hi> muſt adde one reaſon more, in reſpect of you my much honoured Lord, your Honours free goodneſſe to mee at my firſt comming to <hi>Saint Georges</hi> in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> now five yeares ſince compleate. The free continuation of your love in ſome diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes falne upon me in the <hi>interim.</hi> And lately your Honors unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved favour in appointing me to this <hi>Service. All theſe</hi> have enioyned me to this Dedication; which <hi>I humbly beſeech your Honor</hi> to accept of, as proceeding from him, whoſe daily praiers, and conſtant indeauours, in the way of all thankefulneſſe and dutifull obſeruance are, and ſhall be during life, ever <hi>yours,</hi> as obliged,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours, and the Cities Chaplaine, to be commanded,</hi> William Freake.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174045:3"/>
            <head>Love and Obedience.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN 14. verſ. 15.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If yee love me, keepe my Commandements: and I will pray unto the Father, and he ſhall give you another Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, that he may abide with you for ever.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Text is <hi>Verbum Dei,</hi> and <hi>Verbum diei,</hi> as a Father ſometimes ſaid in the like caſe; as <hi>the Word of God,</hi> ſo <hi>a Word in ſeaſon,</hi> even a word for the very day; being the firſt words of that portion of ſacred Scripture, which the pious care of our Church hath ſelected to be read unto you, as the Goſpel for this day. In which without any dilatory Preambles, wee have onely theſe 2. generals propounded to our conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<list>
                  <item>1. A Precept.</item>
                  <item>2. A Promiſe.</item>
               </list> The precept ſeeming to be propounded conditionally, as a man would collect from the words at the firſt ſight thereof, <hi>Si me diligatis, If yee love me:</hi> But being indeed (as <hi>Ferus</hi> hath obſerved) a charge inforced by way of Argument drawne <hi>Ex conceſſis,</hi> from the generall and frequent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all the Apoſtles in their profeſſed love to Chriſt, as their Lord and Maſter, <hi>If ye love me, keepe my Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements:</hi> As if our bleſſed Lord had ſayd, Ye all profeſſe to <hi>love me,</hi> and that ye are deſirous to indeare your ſervice by ſome reall teſtimonies thereof unto me: If then ye <hi>love me</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:174045:4"/>as yee profeſſe, yee can no way better ſhew it than by <hi>keeping my Commandements; If ye love me, keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the ſecond generall, it is a promiſe of the ſending downe of the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe deſcending gave occaſion to this Feſtivall which now we celebrate; this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day, by the Churches accompt, whereon the Holy Ghoſt came downe in the forme of cloven tongues of fire, and ſate upon the Apoſtles at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as yee have it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts.</hi> A Day to bee celebrated with a religious obſervance in a double reſpect:</p>
            <p>Firſt, as it is the day (if we underſtand things aright) whereon the <hi>Law</hi> was delivered to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> the fiftieth day after their departure out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which gave name to the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt, Levit.</hi> 23.15, 16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as it is the day upon which the <hi>Goſpell</hi> procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> by the comming downe of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, the third perſon in Trinity, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the ſecond perſon in Trinity, our bleſſed Lord heere in my Text, <hi>If ye love me, &amp;c. Et ego rogabo Patrem, &amp; ille dabit vobis alium paracletum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have the ſecond generall propounded: the precept of our bleſſed Lord, and his gracious promiſe, which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the particulars therein conſiderable, are like to be the ſubject of my diſcourſe, and your attention at this time: Wherein that our joynt indeavours may tend to the glory of our good God, and our mutuall comforts both here and hereafter, may it pleaſe our heavenly Father to aſſiſt me in ſpeaking, and you in hearing, and to ſecond our weake and worthleſſe undertakings by the ſacred influence and holy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of his gracious Spirit, the Comforter in our Text, even for his ſake, who in this Text hath promiſed to pray for us, ſaying, <hi>Ego rogabo Patrem, &amp;c If yee love me, keepe my Commandements; and I will pray, &amp;c.</hi> and of theſe two Generals in their order, beginning with the firſt,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174045:4"/>the Precept, <hi>Si me me diligatis, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Obſervations may be made from this firſt Generall, profitable for inſtruction, for direction comfortable, which I will runne over with what brevity I can: As firſt, from the ſcope and maine intention of the words, I obſerve with <hi>Ferus, Probatio dilectionis eſt exhibitio operis.</hi> The beſt teſtimony of mans love to Almighty God is collected from the ſincerity of mans obedience to Gods revealed Will.</p>
            <p>God is faithfull, (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) keeping covenant and mercy with them that <hi>love him, and keepe his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Deut.</hi> 7.9. as intimating that no profeſſion of love to Almighty God is acceptable in his ſight, where there wanteth a pious reſpect to his holy Commandements. For <hi>what is it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ô</hi> Iſrael <hi>that God requireth of thee, but to love the Lord thy God, and to ſerve him with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule, and that thou keepe the Commandements of the Lord, and his Ordinances which I command thee this day? Deut.</hi> 10.12, 13. As if he ſhould ſay, God requireth nothing of thee but Love, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Therefore in the 11. Chap. of the ſame Booke, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. hee comprehendeth the whole ſumme of Religion in theſe two branches, <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> where having ſaid, <hi>Keepe diligently all the Commandements which I command you to doe,</hi> hee explaineth his meaning in the words following, that is, <hi>To love the Lord your God, and to walke in all his wayes. Deut.</hi> 11.22. Whereunto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth that ſpeech of the beloved Diſciple to the full, I <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.3. <hi>This is the love of God, that we keepe his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements:</hi> Plainely ſhewing the truth of this aſſertion, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from the ſcope of the words, that the beſt Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of mans love to God, is the ſincerity of mans obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Gods revealed Word.</p>
            <p>Which if it be ſo, then wretched is that errour of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of men and women, who contenting themſelves in this caſe with a verball profeſſion, take liberty to ſhame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174045:5"/>the ſame by a diſorderly converſation: whoſe Religion can not better be expreſt, than by comparing it to that language which the Jewiſh children ſpoke in the dayes of <hi>Nehemia, Nehem.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. For as they ſpoke their <hi>Hebrew</hi> in a broken manner, halfe the ſpeech of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> and halfe of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and halfe of <hi>Moab,</hi> and could not ſpeake in the Iewes Language, but according to the language of each people: So too many amongſt us, when they are put to it, to ſpeake out their Religion in their practice, utter it in ſuch a broken manner, ſo mingled with the practice of a prophane life, that they appeare to be meerely <hi>Hybridae,</hi> of a mixt race, as were Iewiſh children; halfe Chriſtian, halfe worldling; whoſe profeſſion and practice being layd together, miſerably ſhame each other.</p>
            <p>Should a man demand this queſtion of the veryeſt Epicure and diſſolute liver, of the griping oppreſſour, or prophane Sabbath-breaker, of the blaſphemous ſwearer, or time-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Atheiſt, if he love God, or not? he will anſwer, that it were pitty of his life elſe: I would then gladly know, what evidence ſuch a perſon can have in his heart, what te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony he can give unto the world, that there is any love of God in him at all, while ſo contemptuouſly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully he continueth to breake Gods <hi>Commandements.</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly men doe not gather Grapes off Thornes, nor Figs off Thiſtles, ſaith our bleſſed Redeemer, <hi>Math.</hi> 7.6. <hi>The tree is knowne by his fruite, and by their fruits yee ſhall know them.</hi> ibid. <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>Mens love to God is beſt diſcerned by their lives and if they love God truely, they wil keepe his Commandements conſcionably. It is a good note of <hi>Muſculus</hi> in his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> upon my Text: <hi>Obſervatio preveptorum Dei, omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Chriſti fidelibus eo loco habenda eſt, ut ſi illa deſit, in ipſam Christi dilectionem peccaſſe convincamur.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable obſervance of Gods Commandements, is ſo materiall and abſolute a marke of a true Chriſtian, as that, where this is wanting, the lives of men convince them to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174045:5"/>their faces, that the love of Chriſt dwelleth not in them. I will conclude this obſervation therefore with that ſaying of St. <hi>John</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.4. He that ſayeth, I know him, and keepeth not his Commandements, the ſame is a liar, and the truth is not in him. Teſtifie therefore, my beloved, I humbly beſeech you, your love to our bleſſed Lord and Redeemer, by yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a carefull and quicke obedience to his holy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demen: for he loveth me not, that keepes not my word, ſaith our Saviour in this <hi>chap. ver.</hi> 24. But if any man love me he will keepe my word, <hi>ibid. v.</hi> 23. and hee that hath my Commandements and keepeth them, is he that loveth mee. <hi>ibid. v.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Which thing we might the rather be induced to do, if we would but duly conſider the force of Chriſts argument, as it is couched in that forme of eloquution which he is pleaſed here to uſe: <hi>ſi me diligatis,</hi> for he ſaith not, <hi>ſi in me credatis;</hi> if ye beleeve in me that I am the Son of God, and Redeemer of the World, then keep my Commandaments: He ſaith not, <hi>quoniam mihi ſerviatis,</hi> becauſe ye here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt your ſelves my ſervants and Diſciples, ſeeing ye cal me Lord and Maſter, therefore keepe my commande ments: he ſaith not, <hi>quoniam poteſtatem meam cognoſcatis,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye know I have power to kill, and power to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, therefore keepe my Commandements; though any of theſe had beene an argument ſtrong enough to have convinced them: but <hi>ſi me diligatis,</hi> if ye love me, &amp;c. as if he had ſaid: yee have ſeene what love I have expreſſed to all of you, how freely I have choſen you, how tenderly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected you, and what care I have to inſtruct you in the knowledge of the things that belong to your ſalvation; and I ſhall ſhortly give you a full and unanſwerable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of my unparaleld love, in giving my life for you, if then ye love me, as ye profeſſe to doe, by that love ye profeſſe to beare me, I adjure and charge ye, thatye keepe my Commandements: An argument (I confeſſe) of ſmall force and validity to a baſe and ſervile nature; but to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174045:6"/>a free-borne and ingenuous diſpoſition, to a ſanctified ſoule, it is an argument of that force, that none can be more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive, none ſo fully prevailent, <hi>Dilectio fortis ut mors,</hi> ſaith the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> 8.6. and where that is the object of our reſpect, it draweth us moſt effectually; I lead them with the cords of a man, even with the bonds of love, ſaith the Lord, concerning Iſrael, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.4. as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating plainly unto us, that as nothing but death can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert that ſoule which truely loveth God from a chearefull and conſcionable obedience to his revealed will. So, no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in this world tyeth the ſoule of a true Chriſtian to ſo ſtrict an obedience, as the ſerious conſiderations of Gods undeſerved love: when a man ſhall conſider truely, (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> expreſſeth it) that <hi>Prior Deus dilexit nos, antus, tantum &amp; gratis, tantillos &amp; tales:</hi> That God ſhould love mankinde, and love him firſt; ſo infinite a Majeſtie, ſuch abject creatures, ſo freely, ſo exceedingly, with ſuch large expreſſion thereof, to thoſe who are every way ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, ſo undeſerving of the leaſt jot, if conſidered in our ſelves. And ſeeing it is true, that <hi>nulla major ad amorem provocatio quam praevenire amando,</hi> as ſaith holy St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> divinely, There is no more kindly attracting of love, than in loving to prevent. We muſt needes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this argument of our bleſſed Lord to be moſt forcible, if rightly underſtood: <hi>ſi me diligatis,</hi> if ye love me, keepe my Commandements: And conclude with <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his owne words in the ſame place, <hi>Nimis durus eſt qui amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem etiamſi nolebat impendere, nolit rependere,</hi> That man is compoſed of too hard a mettall, who though he like not to love firſt, will not requite it and love againe, either firſt or ſecond.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And yet it were ſome diminution to the ſtrength of this argument; if our Bleſſed Lord in this his love to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde ſhould any way appeare to reſpect his owne benefit. But ſee the freedome of his love, and thence obſerve yet a further force in Chriſts argument: <hi>Chriſtus non ſibi utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174045:6"/>quaerit, ſed nobis: nos illi non incommodamus praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ejus negligendo, ſed nobis ipſts,</hi> ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi> upon this place: As our bleſſed Lord in backing this precept by an argument drawne from his love, doth no way aime at his owne benefit, but at ours: So we, by detracting our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from his commandement, can no way diſadvantage him, but our ſelves onely, and theharme that growes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of reflects upon us, and the loſſe will, undoubtedly, bee ſet upon our ſcore. That which mooved our bleſſed Lord to take our nature upon him, to fulfill the Law for us, and yet to ſuffer as a tranſgreſſor of the Law, was nothing elſe (as Biſhop <hi>Anſelm</hi> wel obſerved) but <hi>amor &amp; ſitis ſalutis hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae,</hi> Chriſt Ieſus, his loving and thirſty deſire to reſcue falling man-kinde from eternall perdition: Which occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that Father thus to expreſſe his admiration: <hi>O chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas divina, quam magnum eſt tuum vinoulum,</hi> O moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and loving Lord, how ſtrict was that bond wherewith thy divine love did voluntarily oblige thee in the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of periſhing man-kind: <hi>Tu Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad terram traxiſti, tu aed columna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ligaſti, tu cruci afixiſti, tu in ſep ulchro claeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſti, tu ad inferos detruſiſti.</hi> It was thy love oh bleſſed Lord, that drew thee the Son of God to come down from heaven to earth, that tyed thee to the Pillar, that nayled thee to the Croſſe, that ſhut thee for a while into the grave, that expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee to ſuffer the paines of hel for us in thy drooping agony. That the love of Chriſt, whereby he purchaſed us to himſelfe might appeare in all reſpects to bee free and ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous, and become an indiſſoluble tye and obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us for a conſtant and conſcionable retribution of love to him in keeping his Commandements. Give me leave then ſo farre as I can, to ſtrike this nayle to the head in the words of the ſame Father. <hi>O longe graviores ſaxo &amp; plumbo, quos tanti amoris vinculum, non trahit ſurſum ad Deum, ex quo prius traxit Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deorſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad homines.</hi> Thoſe ſoules are undoubtedly, more ſenceleſſe than ſtones, more ponderous than lead, whom the tye of ſo free and unparaleld a love,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174045:7"/>cannot lift upwards to God, which formerly drew God downwards to man. Thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrangely froze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their dregs <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.12. upon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ived<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h not work, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſideration of Chriſts love, ſo amply demonſtrated, doth not perſwade to a full reſolution of ſoule to teſtifie a full retribution of love to him, by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obſervance of his holy will.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And that ſo much the rather too, becauſe (as a grave Expoſitor upon this place well obſerveth) our Saviour Chriſt ſaith not, <hi>ſi timeatis,</hi> if ye feare me, but <hi>ſi diligatis,</hi> if ye love me, keepe my Commandements. <hi>Talem enim Chriſtus exigit obſervantia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non quae a timore ſervili extorqueatur ſed ab amore filiali ultrò naſcatur,</hi> ſaith the ſame Expoſitor: for our bleſſed Saviour exacts no ſuch an obedience to his Lawes, as hath need to be extorted from a ſervile feare; ſuch an obedience as the Spaniſh Clergy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth from their people by the power of their inquiſition, but ſuch an obedience as floweth freely and ſpontaneouſly from the fountaine of a filiall and ſonne-like feare. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus non probat obedientiam coactam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi> upon this place very well to our purpoſe: Chriſt never approved of any conſtrained obedience, which had need to be wreſted from the unwilling hand of the performer: he hath done e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to winne the world, and to draw all men to him by love, if he had not to doe with a ſtiffe-necked people, and a ſtony-hearted generation. His word and Goſpell where it is truely and powerfully preacht in the liberty thereof, hath no neede of any Ieſuiticall inſinuations, or rules drawne from <hi>Matchievel</hi> for the eſtabliſhing of his kingdome: If therefore that diſloyall brood of <hi>Inigo Loiola</hi> that lame Spaniſh Souldier, which in this laſt Century of yeares hath ſo much troubled all Chriſtendome, and almoſt the whole world about the erecting of a fift Monarchy, covering all their lawleſſe deſignes under the moſt ſacred name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſhall in Gods good time, finde the all-ruling providence to turne their Councels into fooliſhnes, as as he ſometimes did
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174045:7"/>
               <hi>Achitophels,</hi> becauſe as he would have ſet up a rebellious <hi>Abſolom</hi> againſt <hi>Dauid;</hi> ſo they would plant a politicke <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> but in flat oppoſition to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Son of <hi>David</hi> and our bleſſed Lord; let it appeare no ſtrange thing to thoſe that feare God, however it ſeeme improbable to fleſh and blood: Our bleſſed Lord never warranted nor approved of ſuch a courſe to fetch in all Nations to a formall profeſſion of Chriſtianity onely, without the lively practice of it, or to force men to an approbation of that Religion outwardly, which inwardly they abhorre, if they durſt but to deſpute the ſame, or could be admitted to receive better inſtruction without loſſe of life and goods: <hi>Fieri non poteſt ut man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datis divinis ritè obſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>detur, niſi animo ſpontaneo ex ſpirita dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis obtemporetur.</hi> Mans obedience to Gods command can never be ſincere, except it proceed freely from the ſpirit of love; and where this motive of our bleſſed Saviour will not work, the power and policy of all the world will prove but loſt labour. Our Saviour, without all queſtion, knew what would draw his choſen people to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his bleſſed will, and that is a ſad and due conſideration of his unparaleld love to man-kind; and therefore he ſaid not, <hi>ſi timeatis,</hi> but <hi>ſi diligatis,</hi> if yee love me, keepe my commandements.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But here againe, it is not unworthy your conſideration, that our bleſſed Saviour ſaith not <hi>ſervate praecepta hominum,</hi> if ye love mee, keepe the commandements of men; but if yee love me, keepe my Commandements: For, in vaine doe they worſhip God, ſaith our Saviour, who teach for Doctrines the traditions of men. It was that, for which God complained of the Iewiſh Nation in the daies of <hi>Jſaiah, Iſaiah</hi> 29.13. That their feare towards him was taught by the precepts of men; which practiſe, what fruit it produced in that people, the Lord tels us plainely in the former verſes of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: For viſion becommeth in a ſhort time, to ſuch, among whom this courſe is taken as the words of a booke that is ſeal'd up, which they deliver to one that can read ſaying, Read this I pray thee, <hi>verſe</hi> 11. who makes anſwer, I cannot read, becauſe it is ſeal'd. So in a while it commeth to paſſe, that the booke is delivered to one that cannot read, ſaying, Reade this I pray thee, and he ſhall anſwer plainely, I cannot reade. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. An entermingling of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mane precepts with divine truthes, breedes a neglect of the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and then growes up quickly ſuperſtition and will-worſhip, which produceth in time palpable and groſſe ignorance, not in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174045:8"/>people onely, but alſo in the Prieſts: So that the complaint may be taken up, which the ſame Prophet maketh in the ſame chapter, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their teachers; Stay your ſelves and wonder, they are blinde and make you blinde; they are drunke, but not with wine; they ſtagger, but not with ſtrong drinke, for the Lord hath covered them with the ſpirit of ſlumber. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. And as concerning both Prieſts and people together, that word may be pronounced which followes, <hi>chapter</hi> 13. They come neare unto God with their mouthes, but their hearts are farre from him, meere formallity eating out all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allity in the courſe of religion, where humane inventions are taught for doctrines, and mens feare towards God is taught by the precepts of men: Therefore our bleſſed Lord ſaith not, <hi>ſeruate praecepta ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum,</hi> but if yee love me, keepe my Commandements.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And as <hi>Muſculus</hi> obſerves further; <hi>Servate praecepta mea non diſputate tantum,</hi> Make not religion the ſubject of your diſcourſe and diſpute onely, but of your life and practiſe, not the fewell one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of faction by way of argument and controverſie, but the rule and ſquare of your religious and Chriſtian performances. It was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the complaint of a reverend Divine of <hi>Germany,</hi> concerning the Prelates of his time: <hi>Hodie praelati multa diſputant de authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate &amp; poteſtate Eccleſiae, parum de obedientia Deo praestanda ſolliciti:</hi> His meaning was, that many of their greateſt Church-men, ſpent their time almoſt wholly in acute and ſubtile diſputations tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the power and authority of the Church, but ſeldome, or never, tooke care to inſtruct their people in their obedience to Almighty God. Brethren, I could wiſh our owne times had not a touch of this fault, wherein wee have too many, who too much truſting to their owne acuteneſſe, make a practice to broach nice and diſputable queſtions, that therein they may imbroile mens faith and religion, and in troubled waters fiſh out their owne ends, with their Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing cries calling men away from keeping Chriſts Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their lives and actions, to a fruitleſſe jangling, that ſerves to no other end, but to ſtirre up paſſion without edification. For the ſtopping of which unneceſſary and unprofitable diſputes, our bleſſed Lord ſaith not, if yee love me, obey my will: for then ſaith <hi>Muſculus,</hi> the Diſciples might have replyed, <hi>quae tua voluntas Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine?</hi> Lord what is thy will? but <hi>Servate praeceptamea,</hi> keepe my Commandements, ſhew your ſelves my Diſciples by your obedience to the revealed will of my Father: therein taking away all preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174045:8"/>of doubting, all occaſions of of diſpute concerning his will and pleaſure: ſo that whoſoever ſhall raiſe any controverſie touching that obedience which our Saviour requireth in this divine charge, hath his mouth fully ſtopt by that anſwer which our bleſſed Lord ſometimes gave to the young man. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Nôſti praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Thou knoweſt the Commandements: And if ye love me, keepe my Commandements.</hi> I will end therefore all that I have to ſay of this firſt Generall, with that of the acute French man <hi>Ardentius, Effectus verae dilectionis Dei, eſt obſervatio mandatorum: The moſt infallible effect of the love of God in the heart of man, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable obſervance of Gods Commandements;</hi> proceeding from love not forced by any politick compulſion, ariſing meerely from a ſenſe and acknowledgment of the unſpeakable love which God hath ſhewed to us firſt, and expreſt in a religious obſervation not of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane traditions, but of Gods revealed Will; not diſputing thereof onely, but expreſſing the power of it in our lives and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And this is that love which our bleſſed Lord requireth, when he ſaith in our Text, <hi>If ye love me, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo from the firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall the Precept, I proceed to the ſecond, the Promiſe, <hi>Et ego ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabo Patrem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſubſtance whereof is the promiſe of our bleſſed Lord to his Diſciples, touching the miſſion or ſending of the Holy Ghoſt, which as upon this day being performed, occaſioneth this Feſtivall. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are ſundry particulars conſiderable, which I will touch briefly, leſt the time out-ſtrip me. And firſt of all theſe two words <hi>Rogabo,</hi> and <hi>Dabit,</hi> that Chriſt <hi>will pray,</hi> and his Father <hi>will give,</hi> doe apparantly evince to each underſtanding ſoule, that the Apoſtles were ſhort in their condition, as no way able to have pleaded the promiſe <hi>Iure meriti,</hi> upon the reality of their owne performance; for ſo they might have fallen ſhort of their expectations.</p>
            <p>It is the free gift of God the Father to give another Comforter, no due debt upon performance of the propounded condition; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith our bleſſed Lord <hi>Dabit, He ſhall give it;</hi> and <hi>Dabit ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganti, He ſhall give it to Chriſts prayer,</hi> rather for his rogation and interceſſion in this caſe, than for any worke or merit in them. Our beſt love and ſervices are not able to weigh it downe <hi>pondere meriti, in the weight of deſert:</hi> it muſt come <hi>Rogatu Chriſti, at Chriſts intreaty,</hi> or it cannot come at all. Leane not then upon merits; Chriſt it is, and his interceſſion that wee muſt ſtand unto in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174045:9"/>this our condition and covenant. And not underſtand this Text thus: (be not miſtaken) as if the ſence were, <hi>You ſhall love me, and keepe my Commandements, and then my Father ſhall be bound to give you his holy Spirit:</hi> But <hi>you ſhall love me, and keepe my Commandements, and then I will pray, and the Father ſhall give when I pray:</hi> None otherwiſe; let the Synagogue of <hi>Rome</hi> gloſſe upon it as they can, the words can beare no other ſence. But here is a doubt caſt by ſome: How can a man <hi>love Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>keepe his Commandements,</hi> before he hath received the Holy Ghoſt, without whom firſt had, certainely we can doe neither. <hi>It is God that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in us both the will and the deed,</hi> Phil. 2.13. <hi>and that of his owne good pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, this ſcruple is eaſily removed, if you take heed to what you read. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Whoſoever hath, to him ſhall bee given, and he ſhall have aboundance.</hi> A promiſe may be made <hi>tam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benti, quam non habenti; Aſwell to him that hath a thing already, as to him that hath it not at all.</hi> To him that hath it in a lower or leſſer meaſure, it may be promiſed that he ſhall have it in a more ample and fuller degree than yet he hath: or to him that hath it in one kinde, a promiſe may be made, that he ſhall have it in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or better kind. For the Spirit is given to all (excepting one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt) according to meaſure: <hi>It was he onely that was annointed with the oyle of gladneſſe above all his fellows.</hi> Pſal. 45. <hi>It is hee onely, of whoſe fulneſſe we all receive. John</hi> 1.16. And where there is meaſure, there are degrees; where there bee degrees of more or leſſe, the more may be well promiſed to him that hath the leſſe: To him who as yet hath it but in a ſtill warme breath, it may well be promiſed in cloven tongues of fire: To him who hath it as the firſt fruits which is an handfull, it may well be promiſed in the whole ſheafe, which filleth the boſome. And thus the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had it from the time that Chriſt breathed on them, ſaying, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive yee the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Iohn 20.22. <hi>in ſome meaſure;</hi> and ſo they might well love him in ſome ſort, and in ſome ſort might keepe his Commandments, and yet be capable of the promiſe of the Comforter in ſome more ample meaſure for all that: ſo that now the doubt is anſwered, and Chriſt may proceed to his Prayer, and we to the conſideration of the further particulars therein comprized, <hi>Ego rogabo Patrem, &amp; ille dabit, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words is a moſt materiall obſervation, touching our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174045:9"/>faith in the bleſſed Trinity: Here is the Article offered, and ſet down in the three Perſons, 1. <hi>Ego,</hi> 2. <hi>Ille,</hi> 3. <hi>Altum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ego rogabo,</hi> there is Chriſt the Sonne: <hi>Jlle dabit, He ſhal give</hi> there is God the Father perſonally named: <hi>Ego rogabo Patrem, &amp; ille dabit:</hi> And <hi>alium Paracletum, another Comforter,</hi> a third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Holy Ghoſt. Here is then one Perſon praying, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prayed unto, the third prayed for. <hi>Filius orans, Pater do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans, Spiritus conſolans:</hi> A moſt plaine ground for the point of the holy Trinity, and a moſt evident diſtinction of the Perſons. And heere this prayer of Chriſt ſets us to ſeeke his other Nature: Here he intreats as inferiour to his Father, which ſheweth him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly man: But in the 26. <hi>verſ.</hi> of the next <hi>Chapter,</hi> as equall to his Father in the nature of God, hee joyneth in this giving with like Authority: <hi>Rogabo</hi> as Man, <hi>Dabo</hi> as God: when that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter ſhall come, whom I will ſend unto you from the Father: And thus finding the Father giving here, and the Sonne ſending there, we have an infallible proofe of the proceeding of the Holy Ghoſt from the Father, and from the Sonne.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt, and his equality to the Father, and to the Sonne, are herein plainely demonſtrated. For our Saviour Chriſt in ſending and procuring a Comforter in his abſence, muſt needs ſend and procure them one equall to himſelfe; one every way as good, or elſe they had changed for the worſe, and ſo might well have prayed him to let his prayer alone; they were better as they were: and if he did not ſend them an equall Comforter, they were like to be at a loſſe. But our Saviour meant not ſo; therefore he ſaith <hi>Another Comforter, which ſhall abide with you for ever; an everlaſting Comforter from the everlaſting Father, the Prince of peace. Iſaiah</hi> 9.6. Theſe things thus cleared, I proceed to ſome doctrinall obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Holy Ghoſt is not given but from the Father, whoſe abſolute gift he is; for <hi>Ille dabit</hi> ſaith my Text, according to that <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>It is our heavenly Father that giveth the holy Ghoſt to them that aske it of him.</hi> And therefore is he called, <hi>The promiſe of the Father. Luke</hi> 24.49. <hi>And that Spirit of Truth which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the Father John</hi> 15.26. And in this <hi>Chapter, ver.</hi> 26 our Saviour ſtiles him <hi>The Comforter,</hi> which is the Holy Ghoſt, whom the Father, ſaith he) will ſend in my Name.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With a grave Expoſitor I here obſerve, <hi>Non dari Spiritum
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174045:10"/>ſanctum, niſi interventu Chriſti Mediatoris: That the Father gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not the holy Spirit unto any, but through the interceſſion of our bleſſed Lord, the Sonne of the Father.</hi> For <hi>Ego rogabo Patrem,</hi> ſaith my Text, <hi>&amp; ille dabit.</hi> Therefore doth he ſtile himſelfe the Doore, beſide whom there is no right entrance to the participation of this divine donation, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.9. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. the eaſer of thoſe that are weary and heavy laden, who never finde true reſt but in this comforter promiſed in the words of this Text: therefore doth he ſtile himſelfe, the way, the truth, and the life, in this <hi>chapter</hi> verſe the ſixth, to ſhew us that there is no way to true life eternall, but by this ſpirit of truth, which proceedeth from the Father and the Sonne, no way to attaine this ſpirit, but by the Sonnes interceſsion to the Father.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is worth your noting to whom this comforter is promiſed; it is onely thoſe who love Ieſus Chriſt, and keep his Commandements, for ſo much the connexion of the two generals in my Text doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently demonſtrate: <hi>If ye love me, &amp;c. J will pray.</hi> Therefore ſaith our Saviour in the verſes after my Text: If any man love me, he will keepe my word, and my Father will love him, and we will come in unto him, and dwell with him. How? my Father will love him, and we will come, &amp;c. <hi>O quanta dignitas, quantus honor Deum dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus &amp; mandata ejus obſervantibus,</hi> ſaith an ancient Father of the Church: What a dignity, what an honour doth accuree to thoſe who love God truely and keepe his Commandements? What ſweetneſſe of comfort can be comparable to this, by retaining the true love of God, as a reſident gueſt in the heart, to have the bleſſed Comforter in my Text, to have the bleſſed Trinity it ſelfe dwelling within us? ſaith <hi>Arden</hi> acutely. This is to have God the Father, by the grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the ſacred influence of his ſanctifiing Spirit ruling, and reigning, and reſiding in our hearts. This is truely to make our ſoules and bodies Temples of the holy Ghoſt, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeake, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. This is to acquire an infallible teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to our owne ſoules, that we are in Chriſt, and Chriſt in us; that the benefit of our Saviours prayer is extended to us, as touching the comforter promiſed in my Text: For, he that keepeth his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements (ſaith St. <hi>Iohu</hi>) dwelleth in him, and he in him, and and hereby ſhall we know that he abideth in us, even by that ſpirit of love and obedience; even by that ſpirit which he hath given us. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.24.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:174045:10"/> 4. We may not omit to take notice, that this bleſſed Spirit is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a comforter, to intimate Chriſts intention in ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding him. In the world yee ſhall have affliction, but be of good cheare, I have overcome the World, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.33. and in the meane while I will pray unto the Father, and he ſhall give you another comforter. Indeede the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the originall, as the learned in the Greeke Language well underſtand, doth in the genuine etymology thereof ſignifie, an advocate, <hi>qui accuſatis &amp; in neceſſitate conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis adſit, &amp; opem ferat proijs loquendo,</hi> ſaith the Etymologiſt: one that may aſſiſt, and plead for ſuch as are accuſed before a Iudge, and ſtand in danger of a cenſure. Therefore doth our Saviour exhort his Diſciples, when after his death they ſhould be called before Kings and Princes for his name ſake, to flye to the advice and aſſiſtance of this holy Advocate, for it is not ye that ſpeake, but the Spirit of God which ſpeaketh in you, ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.18, 19, 20. That we might learn thence, when in our ſupplications to almighty God, we ſhall finde our hearts to be ſtraighted, and our tongs defective in expreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our deſires, to fly for aſſiſtance to this heavenly advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and to invocate him, for he it is alone that helpeth our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he maketh requeſts for the Saints according to the will of God, ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27. And in this caſe, doubtleſſe, ſhall the faithfull ſoule, finde the benefit of this promiſe of our bleſſed Lord in my Text, <hi>Ego rogabo patrem,</hi> when the bluſtring ſtormes of adverſity, or affront of temptation ſhall winnow us as wheate, as our bleſſed Lord told St. <hi>Peter, Luke</hi> 22.31. Let us adhere in faith and obedience to this heavenly advocate; as remembring that he which prayed for St. <hi>Peter,</hi> hath prayed alſo for us, and this his holy advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſhall ſpeak in us, and with us, and for us, <hi>&amp; fides non deficiet,</hi> &amp; our faith ſhal not faile: when that accuſer of the brethren, which is caſt down into the earth, ſhal ſerve thee with a <hi>ſubpoena</hi> in the court of thy owne conſcience, and ſhall ſet all thy ſins in order before thee thereby raiſing within thee thoſe <hi>tempeſtates mentis,</hi> as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſtiles them, thoſe tempeſts in thy ſoule, which ſhall ſhake the very foundation of thy faith &amp; religion: caſt out this ſhoot anchor, &amp; thou maiſt ride out this ſtorm, have recourſe to this heavenly advocate the comforter in my Text, and thou ſhalt overcome all oppoſitions by the blood of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10, 11. He that ſaid <hi>rogabo patrem,</hi> I will pray unto the Father; even he ſhall ſend thee helpe by this holy comforter, whoſe preſence ſhall appeaſe all ſtormes; as it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174045:11"/>was ſayd of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Mark.</hi> 4.39. He ſhall rebuke the winde, and ſay unto the waves peace and be ſtill, and the ſtorme ſhal ceaſe, and a great calme ſhall follow, <hi>Et ille dabit alium paracle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> and he ſhall give thee another comforter, that he might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with thee for ever. But may ſome man ſay, <hi>quare aliuu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racletum,</hi> why another comforter; for is not this the ſame Spirit of God whereby the Patriarchs were taught to beleeve, the Prophets were inſpired, and the Apoſtles guided in their Miniſtry while our Saviour lived amongſt them? I anſwer, hee is doubtleſſe the very ſame: for <hi>He is the Lord that changeth not.</hi> Mal. 3.6.</p>
            <p>But this diſtinction is added, (as the Fathers have well obſerved) as to diſtinguiſh the Perſons in Trinity, ſo to proove the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt: He is <hi>Alius Paracletus, another Comforter,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not the Father, nor the Sonne, but the Holy Ghoſt, the third perſon in Trinity. And yet it is alſo added, to proove the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Deity, God, equall with the Father, and with the Son; therefore it is ſaid in the laſt words of my Text, <hi>Manebit in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, He ſhall abide for ever.</hi> But it is alſo ſaid, <hi>Vobiſcum mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, He ſhall abide with you for ever; ut intelligant Diſcipuli,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi> upon this place) <hi>eſſe eum Conſolatorem non tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarium, ſed aeternum.</hi> That his Diſciples might conceive of him as a Comforter not to abide with them for a while, but with the Church of Chriſt for ever. <hi>Ecce, ego ſum vobiſcum omnibus die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad conſummationem ſaeculi,</hi> as Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> renders it: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I am with you unto the end of the world. Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>laſt verſ.</hi> What alwayes art thou with us, even unto the end of the world bleſſed Saviour? Oh ſuffer us to ſpeake unto thee, who are but duſt and aſhes. Thy Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath taught us, that the Heavens muſt containe thee untill that all things be reſtored. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. It is true, Oh bleſſed Ieſus, as thy holy Apoſtle hath taught us, and Lord teach us ever to beleeve, and retaine this truth, that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſhall containe thy body till the reſtauration of all things, that ſo we may be preſerved from that Antichriſtian errour of adoring thy bodily preſence in a Wafer-cake. But thou art ſtill with us, we acknowledge it, and makeſt good thy promiſe untill this day. For except thou (oh Lord) hadſt beene preſent with me, to inſpire my weake meditations in the preparation of my ſelfe for the weighty imployment of this day and houre, through the gracious influence of that bleſſed Comforter in our Text; neither had my heart beene able
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174045:11"/>to conceive, nor my tongue to utter any thing for the glory of thy great Name, the edification of thy people, or the diſcharge of my duty. And hadſt not thou by thine eſpeciall providence and mercy aſſembled theſe thy people in thy Name, by the powerfull perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame moſt bleſſed Comforter: Neither had they beene hearers of thy Word at this time.</p>
            <p>We humbly praiſe thy holy Name for all thy mercies, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly for that of this day and houre, beſeeching thee to adde the operation of thy bleſſed Spirit to theſe outward meanes in ſuch free favour affoorded us, and to perſwade all our hearts, that as we profeſſe to love thee as thy Diſciples, ſo we may ever be carefull to expreſſe our love unto thee in a conſcionable obſervance of thy holy Commandments, that ſo we may be partakers of the comforts of thy gracious promiſe, thy bleſſed Spirit of grace, which may abide with us for ever, <hi>Amen. Even ſo come Lord Jeſus.</hi> And ſo I have done with the Text, one word onely for the occaſion of our mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and ſo an end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The memoriall of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed,</hi> ſaith the wiſe man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7</note> as whoſe good deeds deſerve to be had in everlaſting reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance. I can not therfore in this grave and honored aſſembly, without a ſinfull over-ſight and neglect of my duty, omit the memoriall of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and worthy Citizen Sir <hi>Thomas Rowe,</hi> whoſe piety and religious care occaſioned this Sermon, and this meeting this day. For in the Chronicles of this City I read lately, that in the yeare 1569. Sir <hi>Thomas Rowe,</hi> Cittizen and Merchant-taylor, and at that time Lord Major of this honourable City in a pious care to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate a great number of Pariſhes, then in his government touching the decent and orderly buriall of their dead, did of his owne free charge and bounteous liberality, incloſe a parcell of ground neare the Hoſpitall of <hi>Bethlem,</hi> and cauſed the ſame to be conſecrated for a place of Burial for ſuch Pariſhes as in that caſe were ſtraitned. A motion, (doubtleſſe) proceeding from the ſacred direction of this heavenly Comforter.</p>
            <p>For ſeeing the men of <hi>Iabeſh Gilead</hi> have that pious act of theirs regiſtred by the Pen of the Holy Ghoſt, in that they took with much danger the body of <hi>Saul,</hi> and the bodies of his Sons from the wall or ſtreete of <hi>Bethſhan,</hi> and were careful to bury them in the land of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> laſt Chap. 3. laſt verſes. I ſee no reaſon but why this pious Act of this honourable Citizen ſhould be yeerely remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174045:12"/>as upon this day and occaſion, by ſuch as ſhall bee called to the duty of this Day, to the glory of God, whoſe holy Spirit moved him to this worke of mercy, for the honour of this City, and of this grave Senate, that among innumerable others hath beene ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with this religious example: and for the incouragement of others to follow his ſteps in good workes of this nature: which that it may be ſo, it is, and ſhall be my dayly prayer, as your unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Chaplaine, that God will continue his mercies to this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable City, in a happy ſucceſſion of good, diſcreete, and religious Governours, under whoſe pious and godly care wee may enjoy in ſucceeding times the comfort of a quiet and happy peace, and live thereby before him in all godlineſſe and honeſty: and that it may pleaſe our heavenly Father to bleſſe the preſent Magiſtrates, and all that ſhall ſucceed them; giving them grace to execute Juſtice, and to maintaine truth: and heerein <hi>Wee beſeech thee to heare us good Lord.</hi> And to this end let us pray as the Church hath piouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed us, in the Collect for this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Almighty God, which as upon this day haſt taught the hearts of thy faithfull people, by ſending unto them the light of thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, grant us by the ſame Spirit to have a right judgement in al things, and evermore to reioyce in his holy comfort, through the merits of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour, <hi>who liveth and reigneth with thee in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the ſame ever one God.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174045:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
